all right here we are again had to reset
some things so we're going to do
something called iteration we got it we
got started with it last time where we
did the whole 0o to 10 or 1 to 10 thing
we started counting and things um and in
a way that one with the cly brackets was
iteration that means it starts with one
thing and it iterates over a thing until
it gets to the last one it's called
iteration um every language has that so
we're going to talk about that um the
next thing we're going to cover besides
iteration which is a of looping is types
so now that we've we've dealt with
numbers and strings and this whole wild
true stuff they're called booleans we've
got our types our three main types and
we'll talk about types and then after
that hopefully we have time in this hour
we're going to talk about something
called parameter expansion and um what
that is is um you know I'll show you
what it is but it's a way of
manipulating
the different strings and types uh to do
different things uh someplace in there
we have to cover arguments uh to to
functions which we haven't covered yet
so uh we'll also go that when we do
parameter expansion that's kind of a
part of that so parameters in general is
is is a part of it so the first thing is
iteration what do we mean by iterate
okay so um when we iterate over a thing
um and be completely honest I don't have
a python version of this um
so we'll make one up let's let's say I
don't know let's do Linux distros all
right is there I'm trying to think of
something that I would want to iterate
over um actually you know what we could
let it iterate over is the files here
let's do that okay so let's say we
wanted to see which one of these files
what its permissions were right now this
this form of iteration I'm about to do
is one of the most powerful most common
things you're going to do on the command
line ever so you do something like this
for I in hello hi n prompt uh Rand
color uh week day you see how it's
completing it when I'm pushing tab
that's because it knows what I want say
do ls- L there's better ways to do this
but I'm just showing you so and then we
want to have I which is the variable up
earlier and then
done now obviously that's a long way to
do that I could have just done LSL star
and that would have done everything in
here or just LSL and that would have
shown you everything in here any one of
those things is faster but you might
want to like iterate over it let me give
you a very practical example let's say
we wanted to rename this and put it
someplace else right so let's make a
directory called uh like
random uh I don't know just like uh temp
here or something all right so just make
a directory uh let's see here let's say
we want to put one of
those profile directory name text MD
yeah right so that's actually a really
good example um so let's say that you
were stupid and you put shell suffixes
on everything or vice
versa okay this is a very common use
case for this so we would say for I in
now I could type them all out right or I
could just use
store and it'll know it'll know
everything that's there and then I can
do Echo I done and so that like repeats
all the things right so that's including
all the hidden things you'll see um and
you know how star glob star gets
expanded depends on your Bachelor C
setting which we'll get to when we go
through the bachelor C at some point but
right now star just means all the stuff
in here um but you could you could also
you know be more precise with this um
there my instinct is to want to do find
here so you know let's do this let's say
he remember that condition we had right
so let's do this let's
say um if if the file well I don't know
let's do let's see what type of file it
is okay so we see that we got a bunch of
asex files none of them are actually a
thing let's see which ones are
executable maybe we could do that let's
do LS um ls- l we send that all
through um okay so then let's say well
what if it
has uh an X what if it has an X into it
let's say all the ones that have RW X in
the in there and um you don't know about
GP yet but we can do pipe GP rwx any of
those that have it in there um actually
there's a couple different ways we could
do it but you know there's a million
things so how are we going to do it
let's say I want to do well let's go
back to my original idea let's just say
hello hi N I hate typing this all the
time so we're actually going to do a
list I'm going to show you uh prompts
and Rand color all right so let's see
okay those all that's all of them
right all right so hey bro how you doing
all right so all right we're going to
move those all let's go again so again
I'm doing set- Obi and I'm going back up
I'm pushing the up Arrow which is K and
I'm going to do this again so here I
have them all listed out and I want to
move them I want to move them from let's
do one command first is to test it right
so let's say move
hello to TMP here SL
hello.sh right and let's just test it
you know temp it make sure it's okay and
move here all right so let's actually
move it back move temp here hello now
that's a a very painful you know Command
right because we have to do it a lot um
so and this even better way to do this
this is actually really good segue into
parameter expansion so we could do this
into
this all right so and again I've already
saved this all in get and GitHub so if I
screw it up I'm okay I can go back and
restore it all that's important right
make sure you know that right I mean I
could totally screw this up and just
restore it so now now what now let's go
ahead and do it let's say I want to take
that command I just did but now I want
to do it for everything so let's go find
the command I just did or I and hello I
and N prompt Rand Rand color and weekday
we forgot
one and I want to move it so I want to
move now this is something I normally do
because I'm too scared I'll do Echo
first and I'll do Echo MB space I to I
do
H all right now when I run that it just
prints out what the command would be
it's kind of a nice way to dry run a
thing right now if it's really
complicated this doesn't work right
because there's too many things in there
and maybe there's a semicon or whatever
but in terms of like on liners this is
really great because this lets you you
know you can see what it's going to do
before it's going to do it you can just
be absolutely sure because this is you
know this is a command line This is
there's no take backbacks here I mean
there is git there's always git but but
still you know you you don't want to get
in the habit of doing something stupid
and testing out so so now that I look
that looks pretty good well I already
saw a mistake I didn't move it into the
other directory right and by the way I
don't want to move it I just want to
copy it right let's just copy it instead
so let's copy it and let's put it in TMP
here slash let's run that again okay so
that's the commands that are going to
get executed and now I just delete the
copy the echo so that was DW for that
and then we enter that and we run it and
this is what I'm talking about look at
how fast it ran so we can tree temp here
and you can see there's all the programs
they're alive and happy in there and
they're doing you know exactly what we
said that that is iteration okay now
let's say that we didn't have to want to
type that in every time now I don't mind
that because I can always go back in
history and find that command again but
let's say you wanted to save all of that
that list right well we already know how
to do this so you guys remember how do
you save a list well I can go I can kind
of cheat and I can still this line here
and I can delete all the stuff around it
because I'm using VI again I'm using VI
in the history so I can edit it just
like VI and and then I'm going to do
this so I'm going to say my list equals
and I'm putting uh parentheses around
it did I say that right yeah parenthesis
and then I hit
enter okay now if I echo my list you
might not you might not be what you
think
okay you see what it just did it only
showed me the first thing right and
that's because this is one of the new
types that we have we've already talked
about it but let's talk more about it
now my list is an array it's
specifically it's an array and so we're
going to say in order to deal with an
array there's a very specific syntax in
bash every language has a specific
Syntax for this stuff usually but in our
case it's a very weird syntax but I have
to show it to you and that is you put
the you put the you know the parenthesis
I mean the double the Cur bracket
surrounded and then you put here and you
put an at sign and that stand at is in
at is array right and so when you Echo
that that'll Echo the whole thing okay
that is identical to the same thing
above so I can do for this for I in and
you know my list do Echo I say Echo See
Echo I
done okay now we haven't talked about
the different ways of handling white
space yet this is not a concern in this
case because there's nothing that has a
space in
it we're going to get there I promise
we're going to talk about what happens
if a thing has space in the name it's
actually a big problem and you got to be
careful of that particularly if you're
using W 2 or something that where that's
that's common to have spaces in the
names um all right so but you know as it
is right now that's not too bad a thing
it's not going to you know blow up on us
um but what happens if we put quotes
around it let's just see what happens
okay it still works right that still
works that's actually saf um and but
there is another one too and I just want
to show you what happens if I put a star
here oh what happened
there look at that closely what
happen so it only did one
iteration why did it only do one
iteration so this is a very specific
bash piece of magic
when you use the star and a lot of Pros
who don't know this when you use the
star whether it's an array or it's a
default arguments array it means take
all of these things even if they have
white space in between them join them
all together and consider them one
string
okay that is important because as you
can see it's now turned all of that into
a single thing okay and um so it's
probably about time to tell you the
difference here so the at
is what's I think it's called Whit space
aware I think it's I think that's the
name of it but it means that when you
add an at it means it takes anything
that's got a space and it treats each
individual item as a separate field
argument whatever you want to call it
it's separate thing and so it starts to
treat it separately so it's probably
time to start telling you about
something some special arguments some
special
parameters uh parameters and arguments
parameters are are basically slots into
which you put
arguments uh in any language so you can
think of the the parameters is being
like if you imagine you have a machine
you know the parameters are the the
labeled um you know slots into which
you're going to put a thing uh which
become variables within the machine
itself at that within that scope and
then the arguments are the the coins
that go in okay so so that's important
that you can distinguish those two why
is
why is my Chloe talking to
me
oh all right Chloe Chloe's like talking
to me a lot I don't know what she's
talking about okay anyway so that's what
we talk about when we talk about
parameters parameters are you know named
boxes or holes into which you place
things specifically related to a command
or a function or procedure something
that runs and so what do I mean by that
so you can actually see that
um so this is related to iteration
because as you saw already when we
iterate over a list which is really the
main thing that we're iterating over uh
that's what we're doing and we at the
end of the last video before I go down
another rabbit hole at the end of last
video we used a command in posic Shell
called scq and we did one and then 10
and we did that that's all it is it's a
command that spits out you know one
after the other and so when you put that
into into here or I in blah it doesn't
care right so after in after
in uh whatever is there if it's
separated by space it will get iterated
over and that includes something that
might have you know that's why you have
to put quotes around stuff usually
because because it's you know it's it's
going to squish them together and break
it up so do Echo
I done uh okay so that's interesting
what did that do it didn't do what we
wanted right because it didn't make it
into it didn't run it so you'll you'll
generally see this um back ticks are
almost exactly the same as this and this
is what you learn this is what you
should use this is what show fmt will
change it into back ticks are
problematic because they don't have
double quote context and you know about
that now but so don't use back ticks
unless you really want to and you're you
know it is a little bit faster to type
but um you know you generally speaking
you want to do the same thing here so
what this does is this runs the program
as you already know and replaces it at
that spot with a bunch of thing now if
you put if you put this this this gets
kind of interesting though if you put
that inside of this now it's all it's
it's no longer a thing because it's not
being expanded right so now it's turning
it into a single string and joining it
all together the same is true for this
stuff we were doing with the list so
here we have my list and then we have my
list here so it's joining it together
even if they're it's still considering
it one variable all right um it's really
important that you understand that
because that is one of the biggest
sources of bugs and security holes in
Shell Code because people don't know
what they're doing with the star uh and
they don't know the difference between
the two so now you do and you can start
you know going to the next step so
having said that now we know how to make
how to handle arguments on the command
line so let's talk about that really
quickly I mean everything I just did by
the way we could we could put into uh
you know a program that that four
iteration that I'm doing I almost never
put that into a program because it's
almost always um you know something you
can just run right here there's another
thing you can do too um you know you
could you could have just done star or
you could do an
ls-1 uh you could do I don't know any
any command that you have that outputs
the strings with spaces between can be
used for your iteration right so um you
know and that you know and you can you
can do kind of thing different things
here in fact uh let me show you so I
already have another I already have
another program that I can run here and
this will actually
whoops uh H
title let's try this one um
I think I have to actually pass the
thing yeah I do so you can actually well
we haven't done this yet but I'll show
you oh I just did the first one okay so
yeah we have the start but if we do the
the the the at sign where is it there we
go so now you know you can you can see
how you can kind of play with this sort
of thing um we are going to get to IND
Direction in a second that's what those
less than or greater than signs are
about and we that's related to standard
in standard out and Standard air uh okay
so next we got our iteration going on um
but you know what what does that even
mean let's let's make a new program
we're going to call this program args
okay and it this is just something I've
been doing it's kind of a
traditional uh args a
RGS and um it's kind of a pirate thing
if you want to have a neonic device Sy
of pirates uh you know mod plus X args
and we're going to make an args uh
program so we do the shebang again this
is repetition so uh user binv you should
be able to remember that by now bash and
then we have the args right so and this
is remember that the dollar
thing okay so let's open that again now
it doesn't like it why doesn't it like
it because it wants it to be quoted like
I said so let's go ahead and put double
quotes around it and now when we run it
uh which we don't have to do that we can
just do args it it doesn't print
anything why not because this program is
designed to print all the arguments that
are passed to it so one two
three um and so you see that it printed
them all on the same line right so the
question is are they independent or not
good question right and um something
interesting here watch happens if you do
printf um I'm still going to do it
anyway I don't care so you see how it
only printed the first one that
time this is super important because it
took the first one and then used the
second two as arguments to the first one
so you know you got to be careful with
these but let's try our for Loop now so
four for I in this we already did this
so you should know what this does Echo I
and now when we run it we get one two
three you see how it does each one
individually if you change it to a star
you can probably guess what it's going
to
do because we already know it's going to
put them all together
right and
um actually that was not what we wanted
we want that so that that is okay there
there we go see how it's all one word
right and if you if you're not sure what
it's doing you you can actually you know
make it put a quote around it just to
give you kind of a a sense of it right
and if you run it like this you'll see
that it's actually a single
argument versus you know if you put a a
a an ad sign and you'll see it's three
distinct
things and that's like super important
that you get that so once you have that
understood then you can kind of get a
sense of how these things are combined
and how we iterate over arguments okay
so the last thing to talk about with
arguments are so and by the way we can
use this uh in conjunction with like
some sort of counter um if we wanted to
we could say we could say uh let's say I
don't know item equals one right so
we'll say the first item is one and then
we're going to say uh item Plus+ at the
end you already know about these number
things so now we're going to add one to
it and we can say e
item you know um let's say you can say
argument uh argument uh
number um
item is whatever right and you can run
it this argument number one is one two
three okay now okay so this now you have
something kind of fun that you've just
made that you can kind of experiment
with what happens if you start messing
with the arguments so that's why we
wrote this and if you want you put some
color in there but we're not going to do
that for right now so if you want to put
some what happens if I put quotes around
the whole thing can you can you predict
what's going to happen probably you get
one argument right just a single
argument it's not AR argument it's
argument Rob okay
so and uh so there you go that's one
argument right what if I if I go back to
this right this all three arguments what
if I take two of these and put them in
quotes now what can you guess you get
two arguments all right what if I take
these and I put quotes inside of the
internal one I get two arguments still
kind of a weird second argument right
but it's still two arguments what if I
do this so actually let's let's just
just let's play around with some real
stuff here let's do this let's touch a
file touch uh some stupid
file that's got spaces which is really
anti- Unix don't do that it's a bad idea
that you can never tell just by looking
at that right that that's a thing but it
is okay so if I do for I
in um star do Echo I
done you'll see that it's a thing it's a
file but you know it gets kind of messy
right what if the file name has a
command in it I mean you can see this
gets all kinds of weird because if the
you can actually make I've done this on
accident before but you can make files
that have commands that in them and if
somebody has written a shelf script
incorrectly you can run the commands
just by just when they iterate over the
thing so you know don't do stupid things
so we're going to remove that by the way
how would you remove that this is
actually a question in uh over the wire
and it's a hacker site so how do you
remove that if you don't if you didn't
know about tab completion easiest way if
you ever forget is to just start typing
the thing and hit tab it'll take care of
it for you but if it if you don't if you
don't know that how would you do
that you can probably yes right some
stupid file and that'll remove it and
there's some pretty interesting cases
here like if you if you ever have a file
that's created that it begins with a
dash um it's really hard to get rid of
it's a very that's actually all I'm not
going to give that away because that's
actually a that's actually a thing you
have to do to pass over the wi uh there
is a way to do it but it's pretty tricky
and um because you know once once
something things are named you know
options then The Interpreter has a hard
time knowing what to do so so there all
right so we've got our args here and
we've covered we've covered iteration
we've covered what it means to do
different whites Space versus combined
strings and um you know I'm using
terminology different than what you
might find in the bash man page but this
is the way to go this is it's just
important that you know how to do this
um you can combine counting with
iteration um you can combine math of all
kinds if you want to do this so you can
actually iterate over each one I
actually have a program called total and
it'll iterate over all the lines and
it'll add up all the numbers as it's
going around down a thing uh we're doing
a video and so as it goes down it does
that so that's that's what we're doing
um and that's that's iteration okay so
there that leads us to so you know sort
of the next thing
and I'm I'm I'm debating about whether I
should tell you about addressable um uh
items uh which are kind of like pointers
so the bottom line is I'm just going to
say so you know that it exists but B
we're not going to do it bash has the
ability for you to put the name
um of another
variable into a
variable you know what let me try it let
me see if I can make it happen for you
so so we put name equals
Rob and and then well let me see if I
can just do on the command line so he
say name equals
Rob right and I say Echo
name right and then we say uh name
variable Name Bar name equals name right
and we say
Echo uh VAR
name yeah it did not
work I think it has to be like this
actually it might have to be like
this yeah
nope I don't I can't remember it I gotta
go look it up again no that's how many
characters are in it I'm sorry the
number is how many characters right now
I don't remember I'm going to have to go
look it up I don't use this very often I
think it might I thought it was dollar
dollar dollar
dollar it might only it might actually
that might only be with
um I don't use it very much but it's
important that you know about now I kind
of want to look it
up um how do I pass a variable with the
name of
uh the
[Music]
variable I forgot how to do
this I could have swore it was dollar
dollar I know in Pearl it's dollar
dollar in Pearl it's dollar dollar I
don't know what it is m i it's been a
long time it's been too long since I
used it why would you do this right so
sometimes you might have a bunch of
variables and you want to pick from
among the
variables
um they're using eal never ever use eal
don't do that this is an array which we
haven't done
yet uh no that's that's not don't do
that e Del CLA equals 42 name r name the
ver name equals 42 declare EOD dnamic
name Dynamic ver name equals Dynamic
name declare R name equals 42 Dynamic
name
no way it can't be that
easy is that really
it why ital's
name I don't know let's figure this out
I said I wasn't going to cover it up
because it's very esoteric and here I am
doing
it you yeah I know you can do it I just
don't it's not useful you don't do it
very much you don't do it very much IND
Direction
syntax it's explanation point okay I
thought okay it's exclamation point
there you go
pointer there you go all right so now
you know put that in your notes I need
to put it in my notes I don't use it
very often obviously okay so while we're
at it let's talk about one other one and
that is the number of elements of a
thing okay so if you put um if you put a
hashtag you actually don't need the
other part is exclamation point I know I
finally got there it took me a while
thank you for your patience um so there
we go so this is um name so this says so
how many how many items are in name well
there's only one item in name but if I
were to put how many items are in my
list is it what is it do I have my list
here I thought I had a list did I didn't
I Define a list
where's my
list I thought I made a
list I'm going all the way back
here it is I have my list yeah
echo
echo I think I have to all right I know
what I have to do you have to put the
thing on there I thought you get away
with it in Pearl you can Pearl you don't
need to do this that's why I thought of
it so okay that tells you many things
are there let's try it with name now
though I think it'll tell you how long
it is yes okay so that's the takeaway
put that in your notes hashtag if you
put the hashtag in there it tells you
how many characters are in it if it's a
string or it tells you how many items
are in it if it's a list I don't know
what it does with a number let's figure
that out count equals
2 let's try it
count interesting okay so there's one
thing what if count is like
22 okay count is two
digits what if we declare I
count and now we say count equal 122
12 Echo count is still two interesting
that's interesting that means that uh
that the length is interpreted based on
how many I
characters even if it's an integer if
it's a number um that it uses that's
interesting I never I never that's
curious I just found that out so I've
never had a net need for that but now
you know okay so um
and um what else can we say about that
so speaking of numbers and stuff let's
hit uh the printf thing so there's a
couple things on print up that we didn't
do and um so said hello right so
sometimes knowing how long a thing is
can be useful so like if we
say um I want to print uh you know I
don't know like the
date um actually let's do this let's uh
let's put this into our args program so
our ARS program is already iterating
over the arguments and let's say that we
don't we don't want to just print them
out we want them to be pretty right so
this is something in Sprint if you don't
know and it relates to the to the length
of the variable which is why it's kind
of natural to bring it up
so if you if you do args here and we say
args uh wait where's my other args that
I did I already did
one where is it all right there we go 1
two three we go one two three right so
one
two 13 how about
that I don't know how to count so all
right and it it lines up pretty well and
everything but for some reason you
wanted it to be um you know I mean we
could switch the order let's switch
order right so let's say we wanted to
put the item first
right and we wanted to put it here and
we could put like an
arrow um to
Emoji nope it didn't do it
okay huh my Emojis aren't working right
now anyway so it could
say argument it could say number
whatever number item
right all right so but this this isn't
going to be very pretty right it's going
to be like messed up now what if we
wanted to line them up okay this is a
very common thing in shell and every
other language when you're dealing with
text so I'm going this is the reason to
to primary reason to use printf is this
because now we can take this all and
replace it so the first thing
is put an S here we put our our thing
here and and then we put another another
placeholder here SSS and we put uh this
one wrap it up we got to we
unfortunately got to wrap it up and then
we're going to um wrap this up as well
and now we have a you know a happy thing
we're not using name let's get rid of
that so let's run that all right so uhoh
we didn't put our line returns in there
we forgot I forgot so let's put a line
return in sorry Line Feed and we have
one that that's ugly oh my God that's so
ugly right so ugly we need to make them
line up it's stripping me crazy so let's
do that let's do it let's make them line
up you put them here and you can put I
want to say like 30
right it's like okay but that's kind of
really
weird right first of all it's not left
Justified right so let's do that let's
say let's put a dash in there make it
look just way this is all in man bash if
you need to go look it up you can go
read about it if you ask your AI it'll
help you out but obviously that's like
way too much space so what we need to do
is we need to know how long the longest
one is okay so this is actually a good
case for iteration and we have to do two
passes on the variable this this thing
that we're going to do is is is a common
approach to doing not just this but
other sorts of things later on and
you're going to you're going to want to
do this okay so so um so first things
first we need before we even do the
printing we're going to do two different
Loops okay so we're going to copy this
whole Loop by the way if I want to copy
everything in here I do uh y a that
Yanks all all the actually no let's do y
a it's like all the paragraph there and
I can change it up okay so and it's the
same Loop both times um except for this
time we don't need an item this time we
need to have longest
longest and we'll say we're going to say
what one's longest and then over here
we're we're going to change this but
let's let's comment it out for now you
can either do the other one or you can
just bang you know select and then CMT I
have a comment uh filter for that so you
know however you want to comment it adds
up you so then we have longest and so
what are we going to do here we're not
printing anything now we're saying we're
going to say if and you barely know
about if we did a little bit of if but
we're going to come back to if now
so if is like if um if let's see if we
want to say actually let's use our math
so we'll say if the uh the length of
I uh which is greater than
longest
then by then the longest uh equal
equal
um uh equals I equals the length of I
and actually think we might have to put
this into a variable I don't think we're
going to be able to do this because of
the math thing so I don't know we'll
we'll we'll find out in a second so
I yeah it's probably going to say oh it
worked okay good so you know I don't
think can we get away with
this I think we have to have this here
because it's a it's a special variable
so anyway so that's like the length of
longest and then we can just Echo
longest Echo
longest right so let's do that um so the
longest one is eight characters and you
can actually you can actually put this
into a function which we can do later
but for right now let's just leave it
that way uh you use CMT when uncomment
these that's that's you don't have that
but uh you will
so now what now we need to like go
through these and um we can set up item
item equals
1 or I in
blah and we already have that so now we
can actually do some special things here
instead of having it be
20 um we can
do uh whatever that the longest
is and I think that that will work
unexpected keyword
token oh oh four derp all right so
double quit to prevent globbing all
right so this is like double quoting the
double
quote but uh I don't think I can put
longest just in here I because because
of the S
here I I might be able to though let's
try it I think it's going to yell at me
it's going to say no you can't do that
dude maybe okay look at that so okay so
the the the brackets by the way if you
haven't noticed anytime you wrap any any
variable whatsoever you can put curly
brackets around it to disambiguate it
from the thing that follows um the thing
that follows if it has a DOT or a dash
or something it automatically
disambiguate but if but if it's got like
an s or something like this and yeah you
might want to put those in there and
it's interesting this shell check didn't
yell at me here based on where I put it
because it knows oh hey he wants to put
the longest variable there which which
is kind of cool about sh on shell
check's part so if this worked uh yep
there we go we get we get a nice happy
uh thing that's the right distance away
because we we did a first pass against
the thing to determine how how far out
it was and then we did a second pass
using the longest value to decide
exactly they a perfect one and and I
could be it could
be and and it will still get it right
and it will it will still H put those
things in exactly the right spot so that
there's been a lot of Concepts that we
covered in that particular video um we
still have another 20 minutes or so
before this video is over but um we've
covered you know we went through we did
a little bit of math we did a little bit
of comparison here um and we also did a
little bit of sprintf you know print F
the kind of the way uh that you would um
and again go and all the other languages
have all of these same constructs so you
can use these no matter where you go
when you're doing this this kind of
stuff so let's do something else let's
do so args is done you guys have got
args is now done if you want to get a
sense of how args work you know write
your own and play with it one two three
uh four and this is this is one of the
standard projects I've always done um
and it it shows you which one is your
argument there is one special argument
and um uh so let's let's actually show
you a way that you can use these so in
addition to those numbers that you're
seeing there um you can actually do this
right so um when you're creating an
argument um we're g to we're going to
start so you guys remember prompt
actually prompt be like asked you for an
argument right well what if we made it
so let's
see
um let's see
hello hello okay so hello hello world
let's do this all right we're going to
fix our hello world now instead of
having it say hello world what if we
change world to be uh name right and
then we had Name by default be World
okay so now we can Runo and it says
hello World um why is it not just oh
whoops all right so it said hello world
right but let's what if we wanted to say
that I wanted to just use one of the
arguments okay and we only wanted it to
be the first argument then what could we
do we could say this we could say name
World
equals I mean there's I'm going to do
this the easy way to understand and then
I'm going to do it the hard way so the
easy way would be this so if name equals
world but but but if if there is a
dollar one so um and there's a couple of
things you can do here you can do test
remember we talked about test right you
f test e uh sorry if test
n that means it's not empty uh dollar
one now dollar one is exactly what you
probably
think um then what then we can say name
equals dollar one okay there's actually
a short hand for this it's pretty cool
and I'll show you in a bit but this says
if there's a dollar one use it otherwise
do hello world so we can say hello Rob
instead and it takes it over and it sets
it that what is why did we do this we
did this because you got a chance to see
what dollar one is now what's dollar two
by the way right would it do it no why
not it will do it if I do
this now it's saying hi to whoa it
didn't do
it oh that's because I'm checking for
dollar two yeah let's do dollar
two all right so you get the point so um
so dollar one doll two dollar3 doll four
those are special they go up to 10 I
think and nobody ever goes above that
right usually it's just one but the
point of it is that um so far now you
know every way to get to the arguments
that are passed to a command you know
about dollar uh at sign which is like
all of them you know separated by
whitespace
the you know the dollar star which
combines them all into a single string
as if you pointed you just entered one
argument with quotes around it and you
also now know each individual argument 1
2 3 4 5 6 up to 10 which indicate the
positional arguments the positional
parameter uh the argument that is at
that position separated by white space
and it's important that you realize that
like if I add if I add this here so if I
say Rob uh and Doris right that's not
going to work because it's going to use
a second one now it it will skip over it
if I make this into a single argument
you get the point and by the way this is
another thing where you can test your
args to see what's really the argument
there whereas if you do this like this
you can see that it's breaking them all
down into individual arguments okay so
that that's been how arguments work you
now know everything about them the only
thing left to know about arguments
there's two really important special
arguments um well there's one that we'll
learn much later when we talk about
return codes and errors but the the the
other main one is related to this is
dollar zero so what I want to show you
is this so if I say um let's put this in
our program we going say uh uh the
program name so we can say
Echo uh the program name
uh you know dollar
z
uh uh is and then you
know we can put this we can put let's do
a print up
here let's do a print up let's do a
print up
with no let's we got to we got to look
you can either Escape that let's do an
escape let's just do an
escape all right let's just do an escape
because then we can do this and you can
do this one so this one is escaped and
this one's the actual thing so let's try
that now so let's do back to args okay
so the program name dollar Z is blah and
you see what it did so it gave you the
dollar zero now dollar Z is really
important okay and there's a ton and ton
and ton of of string manipulation
commands you can do here but I'm going
to give you one right off the bat but
this is where parameter expansion comes
in okay and I'm I'm I knew this with
dubil and parameter expansions kind of
so I want to show you that now there is
two ways to do this you could do another
command to get it this is pretty much
the standard way in posic shill which
would would be like this you'd say uh
base name and and that will actually
strip the rest off and it'll just give
you args right so that's called base
name um there's uh another one called
durame you're going to see these all
over the place so uh wait we didn't
quote they they want me to double quote
this yeah so I don't get another shell
extension thing yeah all right so um
there's base name but and I just want to
show you this it's this is obviously not
accurate anymore but if I do this um
it'll tell you the full directory that
it came from right and um if I did do
slash it would do just the this the
small one right so uh the reason it's
showing you the big long one is because
it's resolving the path so let's do base
name
okay so we're going to do that and we
got the base name right so so it says is
args and you see it's stripped off so
the story here you can read about these
but base name base name gives you the
the the base part and the directory name
gives you the part these things work
everywhere postic X and everything but
there's another way to do this that
doesn't involve you know calling out to
a subshell the way we did uh or a
subprocess and we're going to cover that
now so we're going to begin in talking
about parameter expansion so instead of
having base name here we could actually
do this fancy
trick and um I don't know if it actually
works with these parameters I think it
does but we're going to try so we're
going to say I want everything on the
end of it only so I want to go
from uh
uh up to the first
slash right actually no we want the
opposite I always I'm dyslexic bit so I
get these wrong we want to gobble up
everything up until the first slash
that's what this says so let's run that
now we're going to say where's my arcs
all right so Robin Doris in did the same
thing it did the same thing this doesn't
always work because it does require that
there be a slash in there um but it
works right so if if we didn't have that
in there what would it do just to give
you a sense of this if we didn't have
that in there and we just did dollar Z
you already know this but let's do it
anyway before we have before the
parameter expansion and after and before
the parameter expansion it still leaves
it there and it doesn't chop it off okay
this is really really useful when you're
doing things like you wanted to like
rename a bunch of stuff so let me show
you so in temp here let's go into attemp
here and we got all these suffix I told
you suffixes are stupid right and you
want to change them all so watch this
this is amazing okay so now you can say
4 I in N star which is everything in
this directory do Echo I done that's
going to give you all the things right
and but we want to move them so let's
actually build up a command we're going
to say I want to move that up to I want
to move it to this but I want to get rid
of the sh on the end you know where I'm
going with this right so you can do this
you can say I want to get rid of the of
the sh at the end so you do uh percent
Dosh and now you get that with this the
thing chopped off when it okay hashtag
is in the front and and percent is on
the back and if you do two of them it's
hungry that means it goes until the
farest the on it can find if it's not it
just does the first one it finds and
stops okay so that's what this is that's
what this is doing and this this is so
so useful you you will use this so much
you'll be renaming files you'll be
trying to clean up names you'll be able
to try you know put little pieces inside
of the other one and um so this is how
you strip the sopix we already stripped
the prefix which was with a hashtag and
now you know those those two really
esoteric weird things to do there other
languages have stuff like this they have
like suffix and prefix and thing like
that but they don't have a way of like
modifying the variable in place the way
we did with parameter expans
I love it and by the way when I found
out like four years ago that this is
actually supported in posix Unix as well
as bash I wanted to just I was so angry
because I could have been doing this for
years for like literally two decades and
I didn't know so now you know now you
know that there's thing people are using
said and all kinds of crazy crap to do
this when they could have just learned
parameter expansion you will see it go
out go out on stack exchange I promise
you if you get into this and shell
scripting you're going to be watching
stuff on Reddit and they're going to
have these convoluted pipelines with
with said and cut and all this crap and
you now you know parameter expansion
which does it and here's here's the next
thing for parameter expansion it's even
better you can actually do a find and
replace and other people will you said
for this you don't need it let me show
you so like if I wanted to do if I
wanted to say if I wanted to actually
inject and like uh what if let's say I
wanted to replace the I the dot in there
with a dash I don't know why you would
want to do that but let's say you want
to do that right then you do it like
this instead of this you do you do slash
okay that does that only replaces the
first one in this case we only have one
so we don't care you say I want to
replace the first
dot um with a dash and then you hit
enter how cool is that how cool is that
right let's say you want to replace all
of the A's with capital A's right so you
can say a capital A but you see how it
only changed the the the the last one
that's interesting I don't want to
change the last one we want it to change
all of them though let's change all of
them let's do two slashes if we do two
slashes it'll change it should change
all of them it's not changing them
though why is it not changing them all
what am I doing wrong what am I doing
wrong people is it a
g no I must I must have something wrong
here
I thought it was slashes maybe I'm maybe
I'm maybe I'm missing something
here what am I missing it's only doing
the last one isn't
it why is it only doing the last
one here's another one uh and you can
look them all up if you if you do man
bash man bash you can go search for uh
parameter
expansion and it'll go tell you
everything
so here they all
are and there's tiling expansion which
is a different thing uh there we go
parameter expansion so um you can see
there's other stuff here I'm not going
to go into all of it but one of the
things you can do here is you can set a
default value which is very very useful
so if you like want to set a variable to
a default value but you if it has an
environment variable you want it to
overwrite it this is a really common
thing to do here uh you see how it says
use default values the parameter is
unset or nil the expansion word is
substituted okay so this one is actually
really valuable this one right here um
the other ones are different and not all
of them okay here's another one to so
this one will actually replace uh the
exact you know place in the string with
a new thing um again it's like
completely open I know you're a beginner
I just want you to know that this exists
particular and Bash um so that you can
come back to it here's the pointers that
we were talking about um and here's the
length um and the rest of okay so
there's the word one it said it fck the
beginning here's the one at the end and
okay here we go so what am I doing wrong
uh the pattern is expanded is expanded
to produce the pattern of thing
parameters
expanded let's see if pattern is
preceded by a hashtag the third form it
must match at the beginning of the
expanded parameter of value I didn't
know that so it has to be at the
beginning if parameters is preceded by
then it the fourth form it must match at
the end so you can anchor them that's
interesting I didn't realize you can
anchor
them uh I didn't say well you know we
you you'll will you will just if you go
back to the start if you go back to the
start you might understand it so um in
the expansion of the string is null
matches the pattern are deleted if the
string is null blah blah blah
I I feel like I feel like it should be
doing multiple okay this is kind of cool
we're going to do this one next case
mods if you want to like do all lower
all upper this is very valuable we're
going to do that one uh transformation
is Val parameter
blah let's see expansion in the string
the values parameter man this is
crazy the expansion in a string that
that is the value of parameter quoted in
a form that it can be used there's like
so many of these things I don't even
know
yet to all those apply only to
characters at the beginning and the end
not a beded well you that's the thing
there's like multiple different
variations of how you can do it and I
don't I mostly just wanted to make you
aware of it there's command substitution
in The Bash man Page by the way it's
probably worth mentioning now since
we're almost done with the hour that you
can go there's 271 Pages uh written
pages in The Bash man page and there's a
lot of stuff in there there's no way
you're going to cover it all but make
sure you eventually read it all if you
want to actually do bash programming
there's a bunch of really amazing things
in there that you might think are weird
but other things that are useful um
including that's how I discovered um um
tab completion which we'll talk about
another day uh when we do bonsai but but
for right
now yeah right now I'm just kind of
wondering why this isn't this isn't
working I
wonder I wonder if it has to be quoted
it's supposed to replace all of them and
it's only replacing the last
one and I'm a little bit confused by
that I'm like why is it only changing
the last oh I know why because we're
only having it change the last one okay
it's doing exactly what I told it to
okay never mind it's only changing the
last one right it's only changing the
last
one yeah yeah what I was thinking it was
going to do is
this which you know it's not
doing that yeah I was like okay there's
another a you know a that was not
replacing yeah I'm sorry yeah
yeah so you can actually change it
multiple times actually let's do this
let's change it to
e let's keep this one as I let's change
it to e because there's two e's in that
letter in that word I just want to prove
it works okay so you see how that does
it it changed both of the E all right
I'm not going crazy I
thought uh
yeah only be able to operate and buil in
bash command try bashing kind of yeah um
yeah I mean most of the scripting you do
involves combining all the commands so
the reason I'm having you guys learn
these things by in terms of like making
a command and then going forward is
because that's how it's not just about
bash any shell is about pasting together
all of the commands thousands and
thousands of commands are part of the
language because they're all anything
that can be executed on the command line
becomes a part of the language which
means that your Bash
environment your dot files your scripts
are part of an ever increasing language
that you are
writing and if that's not compelling I
don't know what is it's absolutely
amazing how powerful it is you are
literally
increasing the domain specific language
for your usage by BL based on what you
put on the system that is The Wonder of
Unix that is the beauty of Unix it's
just never ending infinite language that
allows through the combination of
everything we've just talked about
through the combination of you know
these things now we we we need to talk
about pipes and redirection we're going
to do that next um we talked about b
bash yes we talked about those
differences already I'll talk about them
again but that was we talked about that
two two two hours ago and there's a
video on that if you want to go if you
anybody who's just joining us just a
plug make sure you go through the
beginner the holiday boost on every one
of the videos and your your answers will
be answered um so somebody's asking
about the difference between bash and
Bash pause for a second do you know the
difference be a good review okay so I
can talk to you about it but one of them
looks it up the other one uses the exact
one and we had a big old long
conversation about that all right so
we're going to end the video now and I'm
G to I'm going to check in with my wife
we're g to if we're going to start a new
video oh guess what my wife just called
so she's on her way home right now all
right we're going to wrap it up talk to
you in a bit